okay well welcome back everyone it's
11:14 we're in our second discussion on
chapter
so before we go to the chapter and
questions does anyone have any comments
or
thoughts otherwise we'll just try to
rapidly address as many questions as
possible
okay onwards
then
so in equation 419 what is the meaning
of the Tilda ETA a component of the
Tilda Epsilon subv okay so tildas are
trajectories Tilda
ATA error minus mean minus
observation or external
State sometimes I remember that because
the um mu and ETA are like inverted of
each
other okay oh okay yeah yeah right but I
but I I I mean there's various notation
sets for internal and external States
but U for mind Eda for environment
exactly exactly but then
e being for for
error yeah but that's
yeah
cool
okay in equation 415 are f and g
associated with VF big F and EF Big G or
is that just a
coincidence that is just a
coincidence s of Rel yeah I I mean
there's there's no problem with adding
more concordances but no the F and the G
have nothing to do it I I think it's
just f ofx
and then picking the next appropriate
letter Jeremy if you if you want to
we're just starting from the bottom just
trying to hit as many of the questions
as possible or feel free to bring up a a
thought
gotcha in the Syntax for describing
[Music]
expectation
no I tried to make these renders a l
Tech but I ended up just messing up the
entire column so no it looks good I like
it with the code blocks
um so I can talk through this
question so there's
the there's the expectation and then the
subscript and then
the um square bracket with the function
inside now no nowhere in the text could
I find an explanation of the subscript
and it appears to
me that that subscript is
more is pretty darn important like it I
would I'm not clear whether that
subscript contains the waiting
Factor um
or or what its relation is to the
variables that you're summing
over so like in my example I I have an X
and A Y in the in the subscript P of X I
think so because there are times that
where that subscript contains um
multiple internal variables so what I'm
trying to get clear is what we are
actually summing over and what the
waiting factor is whether the waiting
factor is included in the square
brackets or
not
um I believe that the
subscript is um what you're summing over
like as if it were below the sigma like
from you know n 1 to Nal
10 and then the waiting is described by
the evaluation of the function across
those those categorical or continuous
values right
well well
my my understanding of the expectation
function is that you
have not
just you have the value at a certain in
um value of x and then you have the
probability of that value and so if you
have a dice a six died dice the
probability is always one over six but
um for our circumstances there's usually
a a higher weight
probability right so
I yeah in this block it's like I'm I'm
just bothered that in that box where
they explain expectation they don't
explain the
subscript um and it's it's causing me a
lot of grief I guess okay I'll
just man go for
it oh did you want to add something
manir okay
yeah box 2.2 could have a definition of
subscript
[Music]
um here's the probability this is the
waiting here's the value of
x here's the probability of X weighted
by their probability and here's summing
overx values and that's the expectation
of
X but you you you're right when you have
two variables that it needs to be
treated a little bit
carefully
okay what is mean what is meant by
Niche simple simply environment of the
agent there's also longer answers I'm
sure people can provide anyone else want
to give a
thought environment of the agent
partially constructed or conformed by
the
agent yeah
maybe possible for them to to modify or
construct
it but but not
necessarily but yes across the
interaction it has to
exist
okay if anyone else wants to to ask a
different question just raise your hand
or go for it otherwise we're just trying
to go to as many of the written
questions as
possible this is in response to the
previous session asking how priors
originate in addition to self-
evidencing optimism bias noted in
Chapter 2 I wanted to mention the notion
of genes and
prior genetic inheritance has been
framed in active as part of Prior belief
that concept itself I was was unable to
find it but believe it was suggested by
Paul
Badcock
yes um we've
done evolutionary models and others have
too where genes provide
priors any other comments people want to
make on
this
okay what is a generative model how is
generative
model related to a generative
process anyone have a thought on
this
okay so the textbook uses this
distinction between a generative model
and a generative process the generative
Model includes the agent model of
observations and also how hidden States
result in those observations so
internally
held variables about external States
um and they distinguish that from
generative process which is the process
that gives rise to the observations that
the agent observes so that's kind of the
um way that the textbook describes
2022 however very importantly in the
subsequent months and
years a lot of people started using
generative model to refer to a system
level description for example here in
guest stream 45 from I guess earlier in
the
year we had Maxwell and Ma speaking
about this and in the the paper on the
inner screen model of Consciousness with
the quantum Fe they use generative model
now to describe the entire
system um so nothing is functionally
different in terms of the particular
partitioning it's just about whether the
generative model is referred to as the
agent and then the generative model is
about the generative process or the
generative Model includes the whole
thing and then you don't even need to
mention the generative process um at 44
minutes in the
transcript at this point right here Ali
asks that exact question to the
authors
so short answer
generative model is coming to be used to
describe all of the system level
descriptions that the model has access
to and then if we're interested in just
the blanket and internal States we call
that the particular States or the thing
if we're interested in just the internal
and the active States we call those the
autonomous States if we're interested in
just the sensor and active states of
course they're just the blanket
States and then if we're interested in
all of the states we can just refer to
the
[Music]
system any comments or
thoughts okay I'm stuck with the
derivation of equation 4 left and 413 I
wrote which part I'm stuck with in the
PDF
cool that looks
awesome
[Music]
um if anybody wants to go through it we
could um but I think let's just save
this
for like I'll just write a comment that
it would greatly benefit from somebody
who wants to look through this
derivation um another nice comment would
might be uh in the
I believe it's in the math group one of
the first links goes through um the P
mdp derivation in more
detail
cool cool to yeah
yeah okay we'll leave this one keep on
going but again if anybody wants another
question just raise your hand and we'll
go for it otherwise just trying
to give a thumbs up to as many questions
as we
can in equation
414 how is the
necessary and sufficient condition
derived why is the
gradient why is the gradient of f being
zero equivalent to having a policy which
follows the soft Max
of negative sign summation of G and
F yeah this is a
good
question
the the fully
updated this is just one possible
reading um when your policy
posterior does not have a
gradient so you're sampling your policy
posterior um at at a
stationerity this
corresponds to the soft
Max um
transformed negative G minus
F
like doing expected free energy updating
of your policies is not resulting in any
changes to the posterior policy
distribution
as scaled by the soft Max which is the
shaky hands
parameter So Soft Max just like it does
in a neural network it sharpens or it
blurs distributions so when there's a
low temperature on decision making
absolute zero then a policy that's
slightly
favored will be like upweighted a lot
whereas in the high temperature decision
making setting the differences amongst
policies are
erased but I'm not 100% sure on this one
let's let's leave
it okay 82 83 the equation says that we
minimize free energy through action yeah
we minimize free energy through two
different mechanisms change the world
change your mind
action on the world action on the mind
and only part of the free energy that
depends directly on action is the lowest
level of
prediction
error in this
setting active inference is just
predictive coding plus reflex arcs what
is implied here that action only happens
at the reflex arc
level does anyone have did anyone ask
this or have a thought on this
um I have a
thought sure is
it well in the predictive coding
Paradigm um you're passing errors and so
the errors are the only way that you get
mind
updates um so is that just just saying
that
[Music]
um the the source of error only happens
at the reflex arc
level
so here in this section it's the it's a
motor a motor reflex so on the on the
bottom level of the hierarchy we have
like the sensory
motor predictive coding is
doing um predictions of of sensory
consequences and then reflex arcs are
basically um
responding just to move to just to
straight without
planning um or deliberation or
counterfactuals the reflex arcs are just
moving to resolve the
difference so simple motor
systems they're um able to be modeled as
predictive coding on the base layer with
proprioception and action plus higher
level reflex
arcs that basically enact default
policies when the set point is deviated
from how do you read interpret the
higher or I key Dynamics visuals 44 and
what does anyone
think um one thing I would like to know
is what the dot versus the arrow is
insinuating that wasn't described in the
L just little dot yeah yeah good
question I mean
one short answer is if you're interested
in message passing
diagrams check out the live stream 55
series because that is the most modern
message passing
representation and how it's being
displayed in the book is just being done
kind of
didactically but the way that the
message passing is done in live stream
55 that's like the real way if you want
to study it from an engineering
perspective briefly um these images show
two ways of looking at hierarchical
predictive processing architectures so
let's just look at this one here so on
the left side we have the kind of all at
once hierarchy so we see a Tilda we know
that Tilda means across multip time
points so what's happening here is we
have these four clusters this is at
level I here's level i+ 1 here's level I
plus 2 so this is a three- layer
predictive processing hierarchy with
observations coming in from the bottom
Through Time o Tilda and the highest
level prior is like a fixed parameter
that's how the highest hyperparameter
works because if you could learn or
update or Draw the highest hyper prior
from another distribution then it would
be another level above it
so the left
representation is showing the highest
hyp of Prior and then the two kind of
thick levels that have this four-fold
Motif involving the um calculation of
Errors between predicted States and
incoming bottomup observations so this
is the all at once
view on the right that has been unfolded
so now we see observation at tus 1 t and
t + 1 so now there's three time steps
from left to right and there still is
the hierarchy from top to
bottom any other thoughts or comments on
it
might want to link to the live stream or
reference that as
um a better
source
box 4.1 says the blanket of variable X
are those variables
that are the uh are the variables that
dot dot dot do Dot and the parents of
X's children the parents of X and's
children are not given a variable are
these not represented the M mark on
blanket formulation if they are where
they show
up
nothing is simply given a variable
whatever the whatever the node is on the
base graph that's the variable used once
the the system of interest is defined by
the modeler then blanket States can be
calculated and the Markoff blanket is
everything you need to make two other
sets of nodes conditionally independent
so that includes not just direct parents
and direct children but also
co-parents I think the specific answer
to the question is it shows up because
the function um Greek p is taken of the
function Greek K
uh in in the variational message par so
that's saying get the parents of all the
children of
X um so it doesn't need its own variable
um because those they're both functions
so so getting the parents of the
children is a double function call okay
okay I think I see yeah yeah the parents
of x p of X or row of X the variables
are caused by X children and the parents
of X's children like you could have
another letter if you wanted to talk
about that
[Music]
um
yeah short answer anytime you're
actually using it you would just use the
variable as defined
locally what's the negative diag in
equation
10 um I think it's a
[Music]
um
Identity or a matrix diag
diagonalization let's see what we wrote
for line
four and not not every equation has this
but of course everyone is encouraged if
they do want to read and help the
equations to write natural language
descriptions using the onology
I'm not sure if this is accurate but
previously we've written
entropy or expected average log prob is
equal to the negative diagonal Vector of
dotproduct of Matrix a and natural log
of
a a is the ambiguity mapping so I think
this operation helps us Define the
ambigu the the entropy of the
ambiguity so if a was just the identity
Matrix that would be the minimum
possible
ambiguity if because just
St States observations would map cleanly
to Hidden States if a were completely
like an even
Matrix like no sensory income inputs
could um could be
differentiated you'd have the highest
possible
entropy in equation 42 there's an equal
sign with a triangle above it what does
it
mean
it means defined by
definition in equation 4.8 in the second
line we are breaking up the
probabilities multip Ling each term in
expected values sumting their components
and so breaking into the composition of
two expected values my question is why
the Q Tilda can be broken down into two
Q tldas with different arguments didn't
we Define it in 4.7 as a product of Q
and A
P why the qila broke into two CU hilders
with different
arguments I'm not sure which Q Tilda is
being broken
up I see that s Tilda conditioned on pi
and S Tilda conditioned upon
observations in pi and those are the
only ones that I
see but the broader point
about developing the um derivations from
this Top Line into all the bottom
lines that sounds like good
work but I'm not sure about this
question because it doesn't look like
you have to split up
anything
in 410 does one sum over tow to get G
the right hand side has a tow indicating
that is calculated at particular time
but G is given by the expectation over
all future
times does one sum over to to get
G
I'm not really sure which right hand
side is being described
here because there's so many lines the
second
line Okay g
subp
what what about
it um this may relate to the difference
between Tao and
T So T is usually used to mean um
simulation time Horizon and too to mean
like agent
time so here the POS the the the the G
calculated on policies which could be
multiple time steps long
is the entropy of the Hidden States on
that policy at that time
plus that sequence of no it's sequence
of times because you're doing a matrix
operation I think it's basically the the
definition of g is uh over a sequence of
to time steps so yeah you're condensing
the the dimension of G is can collapse
because it is by definition over
multiple tow time
steps yeah g has the same G is a
functional that updates the policy prior
into the policy
posterior so
I guess that all the time steps need to
come into play in the evaluation
so each of these but each of these are
at a given time
step but then it's I guess across time
steps but this is definitely not the
fullest explanation of where expected
free energy is
calculated equation 2.6 has a lot more
information on
this
okay I was unable to understand why the
expected free
energy is minimized by selecting
observations that cause a large change
in
belief does anyone have a thought on
this
uh there's multiple paragraphs about it
but essentially look up epistemic
epistemic value anywhere in the
text yeah that's definitely one aspect
of it which is just equation 2.6
Information
Gain policies that result in sequences
of
observations that have a large impact on
inferences about hidden States Through
Time ex Tilda
are loaded with high Information Gain
high epistemic
value so expected free energy is
minimized by selecting observations that
cause a large change in belief yes
that's half the
picture expected free
energy is contributed to by both the
epistemic and the pragmatic
value
what's the role of a generative model in
active inference well we talked about
generative models um
earlier whether we're using the kind of
broader sense of generative model is
describing all of the systems
dependencies or the narrower sense of
generative model like just the agent in
relation with a generative process But
whichever way you take it generative
model is what we build in active
inference no generative model just fun
speculative imagination but this is the
actual object or modeling
artifact can you clarify why marginal
likelihood is called marginal yes great
classical history of Statistics when you
have a piece of graph paper and you have
um events on the rows and columns and
the probabilities of those joint events
in the cells on the graph paper then
when you sum across the side onto the
margin of the paper it's called a
marginal
probability okay we have some questions
with previous upvotes that we could look
at or we could continue on with these
ones that have no upvotes at all does
anyone have any comments or thoughts or
anything uh I have one comment I I'm
still processing the
um the the continuous
derivation um section um there is one
quote that
has I'm trying to grock still which is I
believe the mode of
the let me get my text um it's talking
about
how here we go the motion of the mode
should be the mode of the
motion um
in explaining the simplifications that
allow the uh continuous
derivation um
here if you search the motion of the
mode should be the mode of the motion
yeah this is all related this is leading
up to it okay
okay
um and I'm wondering if there are any
sort of resources to break down
um the derivation of this section in
more
detail similar to how there was with
with the p
DP par mdp yes the most relevant
um
in basy Mechanics for stationary
processes this question of hierarchical
basian
stationeri arises in the generalized
coordinates of
motion so when you have the generalized
coordinates of motion position you know
and higher
derivatives
and you have a
stationerity in that architecture when
the rate of change is zero on two
different levels that are touching each
other that is the situation that's being
addressed
here but this is I feel like if I find a
graph um presentation of what's being
discussed I might be able to get it so
yeah I'll check that out 26
26 um
here are the generalized
coordinates and this is the continuous
time I'm I don't remember what that yeah
not sure how helpful but that at least
is in the B yeah that gives me something
thank you
yep anyone else want to ask a question
okay let's just try to do a few
more basing brain helps us frame
problems that an agent engaging in
active inference must solve broadly
these are problems of inferring states
of the world perception or sense making
and inferring a course of action
planning or decision selection other
than perception and action planning are
there other tasks or challenges at the
brain or organ mechanisms engage in how
would we
know one approach here is just to say
well what are you trying to model just
name your
phenomena and then maybe that can be
cast as a perception or as a planning
task or just more broadly as a sense
making or decision selection
task that's possible because of course
inbound and outbound statistical
dependencies are the fundamental across
the blanket so a huge variety of
phenomena will be addressed by that but
there's no reason to think that that's
all that there
is it just depends what kind of agent
you're trying to model so it's a little
bit too General to talk about all
agents
but are there tasks or challenges that
the brain or organisms engage
in just remains to be seen by somebody
who wants to list out those
phenomena okay for the graphical models
in figure 4.2 what is an intuitive
example for each structure this is a
great basic
question helping get familiar with the
basian graph
formalism like okay I boiled water and
it was hot and it made a sound or I took
two ingredients and I made one
dish but this is kind of the
fundamentals for um all the other Bas
graph
discussions okay this is another great
um basic or consolidating question that
people could give thoughts
on what are the definitions of
variational free energy and expected
free energy what roles do they play
individually or together in active
inference anyone want to give a
thought otherwise this is truly a
fundamental active
question makes me think of like a
class variational free energy equation
2.5 it's the real time gauge on how well
things are going variational free energy
is a functional of only prior beliefs Q
variational beliefs and incoming sensory
data so it computes a measure of how
surprising sensory incomes are as a
function of the agents beliefs at that
time so it's like a diagnostic of
real-time sense making expect Ed free
energy transposes that setting and that
variational basian approach into
counterfactuals of Futures that haven't
happened yet so expected free energy
considers sequences of possible
observables that could happen
conditioned upon different actions that
the entity has the agency select amongst
affordances and those policies are
evaluated in terms of the epistemic and
pragmatic
value and then given the policy
posterior the modular can take different
methods for policy selection like you
could just draw from the policy
posterior or you could select the
highest evaluated
policy
so everything can be understood as
having a variational free energy due to
its persistence through time and certain
kinds of actions selection and planning
agents can be understood as doing
something like expected free energy and
live stream 55 generalized free energy
GFE it may swallow them
both so we may look back on
2023 when we needed to differentiate vfe
and
efe it may just be a transient framing
because
GFE has some advantages relative to both
of
them what is the use of categorical
distributions there statistical
distributions that apply to things that
are categorical
in the
world in message passing is there a
decay of information as the distance
between variable X and the individual
markall blanket constituents increases
is implementation of information Decay
and message passing an option for model
implementation I remember we had some
quite interesting discussions on this in
a
previous
time any thoughts on
this
basian graphs are topological they're
not geometric so it's not exactly clear
what distance means here but let's just
interpret distance topologically like
how many connections the information has
to transfer through then you could
imagine a network that's
lossless at which point the there would
not be a decay of information or
you could imagine a lossy basian graph
where information was
lost is impation is of information Decay
and message passing an option for model
implementation yes you can always
develop models of information
Decay however I would caution message
passing is probably not where that would
happen message passing um is is a very
lowlevel
technique that probably doesn't have any
advantages to Simply have informational
degradation happen
in but ironically or interestingly you
might want to
execute a a a rigorous message passing
schedule to model information Decay on a
base
graph however you wouldn't want to be
information decay in the message passing
you'd want the message passing to
accurately describe the information
decay of the base
graph to update beliefs about policies
we find the posterior that minimizes the
free energy does poster at time T become
a prior at time t plus one
yes
any thoughts or questions people want to
make few more
[Music]
here few more down
here
Q is not a single variable Q is used to
refer to any variational distribution of
choice so it can it can take on
different characteristics it can be
conditioned upon different things as
well you still may have to marginalize
over different
things or condition upon non- different
things
so is Q
Tilda conditioned upon so is Q of X
conditioned on
Pi or Q of O condition on Pi a separate
variational
quantity which is defined in C 410 as
categorical of
O sub
PT
this one no definitely
not it's a separate variational
quality okay policy selection active
inference automatically balances
exploration
exploitation already this is quite a
contentious claim I
mean does it automatically balance it
such that it's
successful or does it give us a pallet
or an
expressivity to set up systems that can
try to balance it I I prefer the second
one but it's written like the first one
one the balance between epistemic and
pragmatic value depends on basically
among other things the intensity of
C this prior is the waiting factor
between exploration and
exploitation
yes the amplitude of
C relates to how much pragmatic value
isal
calulated for the
EF and thus is one
way to tune explore exploit
ballots another way to do it is to
modify the ambiguity of sensory
States what is the difference between
some other formulation for cognitive
agents that places an arbitrary waiting
factor between exploration and
exploitation
the only thing I can think of is e makes
possible variational approximation
methods for optimization which would be
unavailable to an objective function
simply awaited some of the
terms yeah I mean it would be helpful to
provide what cognitive architectures
you're
[Music]
um you're thinking
of for years we've we've as people have
brought up other COG of
architectures like I've here and
elsewhere I've reviewed
them
um there are usually a vast number of
differences between any given cognitive
architectures but as this question
highlights one of them would be a
traditional way to approach this
um problem or
tension is to have an explicit waiting
factor between exploration
exploitation whereas in the in the ACM
generative model you don't have an
explicit tradeoff
Factor you just have the generative
model and then in different
environmental settings it is going to
have different arising
behaviors and it can do the variational
approximation methods
but you could have a cognitive
architecture that was like a variational
autoencoder which would enable you to
use variational
methods so it's not that the only
difference is the variational
methods
any kind of last thoughts or
questions I have a quick question when
we say variational methods doesn't it
really essentially mean that we have a
some kind of uh parameterized model that
we're optimizing through some kind of um
optimization procedure
that's so that would apply to so
effectively like um deep learning um
methods are in in in a sense also
variational
right they they could be and many
R most narrowly it's when the
variational
approximation to exact Bas is
used so not all methods use
variational
approximation so not all deep learning
or statistics are are variational
statistics however broad categories of
them
are so using this variational
autoencoder scheme the
input obviously is the sensory put the
lat and space are the cognitive
States and then the output is the action
selection so all of this which is
otherwise like just an
engineering
sketch all of this is kind of
refined into the first principles basian
mechanics particular partition physics
of cognitive systems path of least
action
all of those
features that's the kind of analytical
setup of active
inference then it it but it neatly
touches to existing architectures like
this but again there's also machine
learning architectures that don't use
variational
methods so it's not simply just being
parametric
[Music]
um
this is a this is a short page but also
a relevant one energy based
models which is funny because they even
talk about generative
models so reproducing data distributions
using these statistically physics based
methods you know there was a there was a
paper that um I don't think made uh much
of a splash but it's really interesting
in the context of
um somewhat somewhat in the context of
active inference is that uh effectively
every classifier um no matter how it's
trained can be seen as an energy based
model and that was the title of the
paper um your classifier is secretly an
energy based model and and you should
treat it as such um
so I think there's some kind of really
interesting deep connection there
between um even a model that's not
explicitly train using variational
methods if you look at through this
through the lens of that paper then
obviously the equation the the equations
for energy based models they look very
much like um the formalism um of uh
based on free energy principle uh I'm
sure there's some interesting nugget of
gold there to to to that that could be
dug out um for someone a little bit more
vers in this mathematically but it's
interesting that the stuff is just
hiding there
yep totally agreed even when the
notation and the ontology look very
different there's no reason to think
that that's the end of the road yeah so
thank you all see you all next time
thank you so much peace by